Guide to the George Burton Adams Papers
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
George Burton Adams papers
1879-1980
MS 30
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
9.42
(17 boxes)
The George Burton Adams Papers consist of approcimately 6,000 items. Includes correspondence concerning English history, the Yale History Department, the relationship of graduate to undergraduate education at Yale and in general, the American Historical Association, and the American Historical Review. Includes correspondence with British and American historians.
Adams, George Burton, 1851-1925
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of George B. Adams and Ruth Adams, 1942.
Scope and Contents
The George Burton Adams Papers consists of approcimately 6,000 items. Includes correspondence concerning English history, the Yale History Department, the relationship of graduate to undergraduate education at Yale and in general, the American Historical Association, and the American Historical Review. Includes correspondence with British and American historians.
Biographical / Historical
Professor of history at Yale University, 1888-1925; Ph.D. University of Leipzig, 1886; editor of American History Review, 1895-1913; editor and author of numerous books and articles.
Arrangement
The Papers of George Burton Adams are filed according to subjects provided by Adams and described in the inventory. The original arrangement provided by Adams has been retained. Because only a part of Adams' papers were given to the library, many of the numerical files are nonexistent. The original numbering has been preserved.
World War, 1914-1918; Educators; Historians; Adams, George Burton, 1851-1925; Yale University -- Curricula; Yale University -- Faculty; Yale University. Department of History; Yale University. Graduate School
- Inventory, 1880-1920
  - American Historical Review, 1904 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - American Historical Association Secondary School Committee, 1897 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - General history high school text, 1898 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - French history - "Story of the French Nation", 1897 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Why Americans dislike England, 1896-1898 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Transfer of French Nation ([Flood and Vincent] Macmillan), 1897 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - American Historical Association, American Historical Review and the question of their union., 1897-1916 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Watson's French history; introduction to Green - Short History of England, 1897-1898 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Jurisprudence section of American Historical Association, 1898 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Union of American Historical Association and American Historical Review, 1898-1899 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Yale graduate courses, 1898-1902 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Charles Scribner's sons, 1898-1908 (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Founding American Historical Review, 1895 (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Medieval history, 1898-1903 (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - European history, 1899-1901 (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - Civilisation During the Middle Ages, 1894-1913 (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - The Yale situation, 1900-1906 (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - Yale History Department, 1909 (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - American Historical Association, 1900-1903 (Box 2, Folder 19)
  - Letters from England and France, 1904-1908 (Box 2, Folder 20)
  - Requests to give addresses in various places, 1897-1921 (Box 3, Folder 21)
  - Revision of text for high schools, especially French history, 1903-1918 (Box 3, Folder 22)
  - Election of managing editor of American Historical Review, et cetera, 1900 (Box 3, Folder 23)
  - Historical fiction, Bemont of Monod and other publications, 1900 (Box 3, Folder 24)
  - Political history of England, 1901-1924 (Box 3, Folder 25)
  - "Documents illustrative of English history", 1902-1922 (Box 3, Folder 26)
  - American Historical Association; membership, cost of magazine, and meeting in New Orleans 1903, 1902-1906 (Box 3, Folder 27)
  - Charles H. Haskins, 1901-1914 (Box 3, Folder 28)
  - Combination of American Historical Review with Carnegie Institute, 1902-1908 (Box 4, Folder 29)
  - J. Horace Round, 1901-1980 (Box 4, Folder 30)
  - History courses at Yale, 1903 (Box 4, Folder 31)
  - Yale History Department, 1900-1919 (Box 4, Folder 32)
  - American Historical Review, 1905-1913 (Box 4, Folder 33)
  - Yale University Library budget and Library Committee, 1905-1912 (Box 4, Folder 34)
  - Letters of recommendation and appointment, 1905-1910 (Box 4, Folder 35)
  - John A. Porter Prize at Yale, 1905-1908 (Box 4, Folder 36)
  - Unfiled letters from others - "Comments on the "Present Problems of Medieval History"", 1906-1924 (Box 4, Folder 37)
  - Unfiled letters from others - "Comments on the "Present Problems of Medieval History"", 1906-1924 (Box 4, Folder 38)
  - Carnegie Institute; American Historical Institute, London, Undated (Box 4, Folder 40)
  - Edward G. Bourne; John S. Bassett, 1907 (Box 4, Folder 42)
  - American Historical Association (2 folders), 1905-1909 (Box 5, Folder 43)
  - Max Farrand, 1908-1910 (Box 5, Folder 44)
  - Charles Seymour, Robert Moses, Stewart L. Mims., 1908-1910 (Box 5, Folder 46)
  - Invitations, requests, 1913-1923 (Box 5, Folder 48)
  - Recommendation and requests, 1909-1921 (Box 5, Folder 49)
  - "The College in the University", 1909 (Box 5, Folder 50)
  - "The College vs. the University", 1909 (Box 5, Folder 51)
  - Yale correspondence, 1910-1911 (Box 5, Folder 52)
  - Yale History Department, 1910-1916 (Box 6, Folder 53)
  - Yale correspondence, 1909-1910 (Box 6, Folder 54)
  - James F. Baldwin, 1911-1919 (Box 6, Folder 55)
  - Yale History publications, 1911-1923 (Box 6, Folder 56)
  - History Teachers Magazine (American Historical Association), 1911-1919 (Box 6, Folder 57)
  - Arden Press; Stanford Summer Schools, 1915-1919 (Box 6, Folder 59)
  - Proposed American Quarterly of European History, 1916-1923 (Box 6, Folder 60)
  - Comments on G. B. A. works, 1914-1916 (Box 6, Folder 61)
  - George Louis Beer; British Empire and Peace negotiations, 1916-1919 (Box 6, Folder 62)
  - George E. Woodbine, 1916-1921 (Box 6, Folder 63)
  - Students; colleagues; "Constitutional History of England' (4 folders), 1911-1920 (Box 7, Folder 64)
  - Yale College, 1904-1913 (Box 7, Folder 89)
  - Notes for book on British Empire, Undated (Box 7, Folder 90)
  - G. B. A. notes and drafts, Undated (Box 7, Folder 91-92)
  - Review of Forrest's "Development of Western Civilasation", 1904 (Box 7, Folder 93)
  - Max Farrand, 1908 (Box 7, Folder 94)
  - G. B. A. Presidential Address (American Historical Association), Undated (Box 7, Folder 126)
  - Day, George Peraley, Dean Oertal; role of graduate schools, 1908-1911 (Box 7, Folder 129)
  - The Nation, 1908-09-03 (Box 7, Folder 130)
  - Examinations, Undated (Box 7, Folder 133)
  - Clippings on Blackstone, Undated (Box 7, Folder 141)
  - Anglo-Saxon, Undated (Box 7, Folder 142)
  - Papal infallibility (clippings), 1892 (Box 7, Folder 143)
  - Indulgences (clippings), 1901 (Box 7, Folder 144)
  - Phillip Schaff "The Oldest Roman Encyclical", Undated (Box 7, Folder 145)
  - Teaching by seminar, 1902-1910 (Box 7, Folder 146)
  - British Constitution 1653, 1897 (Box 7, Folder 149)
  - Yale courses, 1909 (Box 8, Folder 153)
  - Bills, 1902-1906 (Box 8, Folder 154)
  - Gaillard Thomas Lapsley, 1905 (Box 8, Folder 155)
  - Bills, 1907-1909 (Box 8, Folder 160)
  - Teaching versus research, 1909 (Box 8, Folder 161)
  - History honors report, 1909-1912 (Box 8, Folder 162)
  - Henry L. Cannon, 1909 (Box 8, Folder 168)
  - Yale History Department, 1911-1915 (Box 8, Folder 171)
  - Homer J. Webster, 1912 (Box 8, Folder 173)
  - Allen Johnson, 1914 (Box 8, Folder 177)
  - Yale reorganization, Circa 1914 (Box 8, Folder 178)
  - 13th century royal finances, 1912 (Box 8, Folder 179)
  - W. O. Ault, 1917-1924 (Box 8, Folder 180)
  - C. G. Crump, 1916-1921 (Box 8, Folder 181)
  - Royal Historical Society, 1916-1917 (Box 8, Folder 182)
  - "Y" for intellectual achievement, 1917-1923 (Box 8, Folder 183)
  - A. C. McLaughlin, 1918 (Box 8, Folder 184)
  - Pomona College visit January 1917, 1915-1918 (Box 8, Folder 185)
  - William S. Mckechine, 1915-1918 (Box 8, Folder 186)
  - Sterling Requests, 1918 (Box 8, Folder 187)
  - Correspondence: letters to editors, 1915-1918 (Box 8, Folder 190)
  - Article on "Federal Government", 1919 (Box 8, Folder 192)
  - American Historical Association membership, 1919 (Box 8, Folder 193)
  - Edwin S. Corwin, "An Examination of the Covenant", 1919 (Box 8, Folder 194)
  - George F. Molean, 1919 (Box 8, Folder 195)
  - New York University Hall of Fame, 1920 (Box 8, Folder 197)
  - Franklin Bowditch Dexter, 1921 (Box 9, Folder 199)
  - "Constitutional History" comments., 1921 (Box 9, Folder 200)
  - Australia, 1896 (Box 9, Folder 201)
  - Germany and England (clippings), 1897 (Box 9, Folder 202)
  - Course outline, Leipaig University, 1909 (Box 9, Folder 204)
  - Kriehn, 1909 (Box 9, Folder 205a)
  - Riker, 1908-1909 (Box 9, Folder 205b)
  - "London Commune" comments, 1909-1915 (Box 9, Folder 206)
  - Williston Walker, 1908 (Box 9, Folder 207)
  - Allen Johnson, 1909-1910 (Box 9, Folder 210)
  - Walker; Asakawa, 1909-1921 (Box 9, Folder 211)
    Scope and Contents
    Correspondence with Asakawa, Yale President Arthur Twining Hadley, and others regarding Asakawa's research leave and continued appointment in the Yale History Dept. during a time of "appalling deficit" confronting the university.
  - Yale Press, 1910-1921 (Box 9, Folder 212)
  - American Historical Review, 1910-1911 (Box 9, Folder 214)
  - Graduate schools, 1908-1910 (Box 9, Folder 215)
  - Bibliography of American History, Undated (Box 9, Folder 218)
  - Yale Review, 1910 (Box 9, Folder 219)
  - Ph.D. requirements, 1909-1912 (Box 9, Folder 223)
  - Sheffield Scientific School, Undated (Box 9, Folder 224)
  - Henry L. Cannon, 1912-1913 (Box 9, Folder 226)
  - J. M. Fling; Max Farrand, 1912 (Box 9, Folder 227)
  - American Historical Society, 1912 (Box 9, Folder 228)
  - Benjamin Terry; "Origins of the English Constitution", 1912-1916 (Box 9, Folder 229)
  - William MacDonald, 1912 (Box 9, Folder 230)
  - Ph.D., 1912-1914 (Box 9, Folder 231)
  - "Origin of the English Constitution", 1912 (Box 9, Folder 232)
  - Anglo-American Alliance (clippings), 1913 (Box 9, Folder 234)
  - Comments on G. B. A. articles., 1913 (Box 9, Folder 236)
  - Clippings, 1913 (Box 9, Folder 237)
  - America and the Great War, 1918 (Box 10, Folder 238)
  - J. Horace Round, 1914 (Box 10, Folder 239)
  - Sidney K. Mitchell, 1915 (Box 10, Folder 243)
  - Notes and comments on G. B. A. articles, 1914 (Box 10, Folder 244)
  - Albert B. White, 1914-1921 (Box 10, Folder 246)
  - Perrin Galpin, 1914 (Box 10, Folder 248)
  - F. W. Powicke, 1914-1919 (Box 10, Folder 249)
  - Henry Holt and Company; Felik Alcan, 1913-1916 (Box 10, Folder 250)
  - Editing manuscripts, 1922 (Box 10, Folder 251)
  - 1911 coronation (clippings) (Box 10, Folder 252)
  - Speaking requests, 1916 (Box 10, Folder 254)
  - William Howard Taft, 1916 (Box 10, Folder 255)
  - Neutrality clippings, 1916 (Box 10, Folder 256)
  - Anglo-American intellectual links, 1917-1918 (Box 10, Folder 257)
  - The Independent, 1898 (Box 10, Folder 258)
  - C. D. Allin, 1917 (Box 10, Folder 259)
  - W. S. Holdsworth, 1915-1916 (Box 10, Folder 260)
  - Guest lectureships, 1917-1920 (Box 10, Folder 261)
  - "European History; An Outline of its Development", notices and reviews, 1899 (Box 10, Folder 262)
  - "Select Documents of English Constitutional History", 1902 (Box 10, Folder 263)
  - Venezuela question - Monroe Doctrine and Feeling toward England, 1895-1896 (Box 10, Folder 264)
  - Wallace Notestein, 1916-1922 (Box 10, Folder 265)
  - "British Empire and League of Peace" comments, 1918 (Box 11, Folder 266)
  - "Outline Sketch of English Constitutional History" comments, 1918 (Box 11, Folder 267)
  - Charles H. Haskins, 1918 (Box 11, Folder 268)
  - Charles P. Howland, 1918 (Box 11, Folder 269)
  - Yale College versus Yale University, 1906 (Box 11, Folder 270)
  - C. G. Crump, 1919 (Box 11, Folder 271)
  - "The British Empire and A League of Peace" comments, 1918-1919 (Box 11, Folder 272)
  - "The British Empire and A League of Peace" comments, 1918-1919 (Box 11, Folder 273)
  - Thomas William Nadal, Drury College., 1920-1921 (Box 11, Folder 274)
  - Curtis Walker, 1921-1924 (Box 11, Folder 275)
  - National Civic Federation, 1921 (Box 11, Folder 276)
  - Publisher, permissions, 1918-1919 (Box 11, Folder 277)
  - R. R. Schuyler, 1922 (Box 11, Folder 278)
  - "Federal Government: Its Method and Function"; also Free Traders., 1918-1919 (Box 11, Folder 279)
  - Sydney K. Mitchell, 1911 (Box 11, Folder 280)
  - Yale History publication, 1913-1914 (Box 11, Folder 281)
  - Treaty of Versailles, copy; "Federal Government", 1918 (Box 11, Folder 282)
  - Irish question; League of Nations; clippings, 1918 (Box 11, Folder 283)
  - James F. Willard, 1923 (Box 12, Folder 284)
  - Last chapter of "Preservation of American Colleges", Undated, 1911 (Box 12, Folder 285-291)
  - Bill to G. B. A. from Public Records Office, 1909 (Box 12, Folder 292)
  - Photostats of documents from Public Records Office, London, 1940 (Box 12, Folder 293)
  - Joaquin Albarran; Abbott, 1899-1914 (Box 12, Folder 294)
  - Miscellaneous notes of G. B. A., Undated (Box 12, Folder 295-309)
  - Note cards (Box 13)
  - Note cards (Box 14)
  - Note cards (Box 15)
  - Note cards (Box 16)
  - Writings and clippings
    - Wheeler, Theodosia Mary (Davenport), 1879-1906 (Box 17, Folder 310)
    - Wheeler, J. D., 1879, Undated (Box 17, Folder 311)
    - White, H., 1894-1899 (Box 17, Folder 312)
    - Whipple, Amiel W., 1897-1906 (Box 17, Folder 313)
    - White, M. C., 1918 (Box 17, Folder 314)
    - Whidden, Bradlee, 1912 (Box 17, Folder 315)